Okay, today is
בבא מציעא דף ק"ז, Bava Metzia Daf Kuf Zayin, and we're at
the bottom of ק"ז עמוד ב'. Kuf Zayin Amud Bet. Yesterday we
were at the משנה Mishna at the end of the day, but
we'll start there again. So the משנה Mishna begins: המקבל שדה מחבירו
לזרעה שעורים לא יזרענה חטים, Hamakabel sadeh lachaveiro leizra se'orim lo yizra'ena
chitim, חטים יזרענה שעורים, chitim yizra'ena se'orim, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אוסר.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel oser. תבואה לא יזרענה קטנית, Tevuah lo yizra'ena
kitnit, קטנית יזרענה תבואה, kitnit yizra'ena tevuah, ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אוסר.
veRabban Shimon ben Gamliel oser. So
if somebody rents a field in order to plant barley, you're not
allowed to plant wheat because wheat is much worse for the ground
than the barley, or it takes more out of the ground.
However, if you got it to plant wheat, you can plant barley
because wheat is worse and so you can do something that's less
bad for the ground. But רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אוסר. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel oser. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is
of the opposite opinion that you have to if I made the
contract to rent a field in order to plant one thing, I
plant that one thing and otherwise I'm going against the contract.
תבואה לא יזרענה קטנית, Tevuah lo yizra'ena kitnit, קטנית יזרענה תבואה, kitnit
yizra'ena tevuah, ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אוסר. veRabban Shimon ben Gamliel oser.
In general, it also says that cereals,
if cereals are what you're going to plant, grains, then you can't
plant legumes or pulse. But if you made the contract to plant
legumes, you can plant cereal. And again, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אוסר.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel oser. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says no, you have to do what you said you would
do. גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מאי טעמא דרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל? mai ta'ama deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel?
Why does רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel not allow
that? It makes sense that we should say okay, fine, I contracted
for one thing, but this is less bad for your field than
the other thing. The issue isn't that we didn't contract for me
to plant a certain thing, we contracted to plant the field and
it's as much as this, I can do as much as the
thing that takes this much out of the ground. But something that
takes less out of the ground, why should that be a problem?
You should be able to
say זכי ליה לאדם שלא בפניו
אבל
אין חב לשלא בפניו.
zachi leih leadam shelo befanav
aval ein chav leshelo befanav. But דכתיב שארית ישראל לא יעשו עולה
ולא ידברו כזב ולא ימצא בפיהם לשון תרמית. dichtiv She'erit Yisrael lo
ya'asu avlah velo yedabru kazav velo yimatze befihem lashon tarmit. Jews don't
lie. You shouldn't lie, or Jews shouldn't lie. You're not allowed to
do this thing. It's like, why are you making a contract for
one thing and doing another thing? That's wrong.
That's against what God wants.
מיתיבי. Meitivi. Ah, there's a problem with that. מגבת פורים לפורים. Megibat
Purim lePurim. The what you're collecting for פורים Purim is for פורים.
Purim. The צדקה tzedakah that you collect to distribute on פורים Purim
is only for that purpose. ואין מדקדקין בדבר, ve'ein medakdekin badavar, but
you don't you're not so careful about it. ואין העני רשאי ליקח
מהן רצועה לסנדלו. ve'ein he'ani rashai likach mehen retzu'ah lesandalo. But a
poor person can't even take from it a strap for his sandal.
אלא אם כן התנו במעמד אנשי העיר, ela im ken nitnu bema'amad
anshei hair, unless in the town council they said that was okay.
דברי רבי יעקב שאמר משום רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Yaakov she'amar mishum
Rabbi Meir. This is the opinion of רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov in
the name of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל מיקל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel meikel, but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel was lenient and he said you could do that or
you could do something. רש"י Rashi says אף על גב דמשני לא
סבר דמקפדי אינשי מידי דלא חסר ביה.
af al gav de'mashnei lo savar demakpidei
inishei midei delo chasir bei.
He says why are people so careful, you don't have to be
so careful if it's not going to do any damage, then what's
the problem? So why here is he מיקל meikel and there he
is not? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, טעמא דרבי שמעון כדי מר. ta'ama
deRabbi Shimon kedi mar. רבן שמעון's's Rabban Shimon opinion is like my
master's. רבה בר נחמני, Rabbah bar Nachmani,
רש"י Rashi explains who was אביי's Abaye teacher. דאמר מר האי מאן
דניחא ליה דתיפשור ארעיה ליזרע שתא חטי ושתא שערי.
da'amar mar hai man denicha leih detifshir arei lizra shata chitei
veshatat se'orei. Somebody who wants, according to רש"י, Rashi, to hurt his
field should plant in one year wheat and the next year barley.
שתא מהאי גיסא ושתא מהאי גיסא. shatat tivtei veshatat arvei. One year
one wise and the other way perpendicular to that. ולא אמרן אלא
דלא כריב ותני אבל כריב ותני לית
לן
בה.
velo amran ela delo keriv utnei
aval keriv utnei leit lan bah.
And it only counts if you didn't
plow
a second time. But if you plowed a second time after the
planting process, sorry, you planted, you harvested, and then you plowed, planted,
harvested, or planted, plowed, harvested, depending on whether in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael they put the seeds on the ground and then plowed them
under, and outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael which I think was
also the practice in Egypt, I'm getting confused about that. But there's
a רמב"ם Rambam and a רדב"ז Radbaz about it. When we get
to שביעית Shevi'it where they put
חרישה וזריעה charisha u'zria in the wrong order when they talk about
הלכות שביעית Hilchot Shevi'it
because they happened in different orders in different places. The agricultural practice
in one place was what we would expect, which is to plow
the furrows and then put the seeds in the ground, and in
other places they put the seeds on the ground and plowed them
under.
And in any event, I think it's the wrong order in שבת
Shabbat also.
Yeah, it probably is, it should be the same. Right.
So
in any event, here the point is if I plow it before
the planting process and then after I've harvested I plow again, it's
unproblematic because because it doesn't hurt the ground as much.
תוספות Tosafot disagree with... Actually no, planting one year, one year wheat
and one year barley is good for the field to go back
and forth between them. But and so actually האי מאן דניחא ליה
דטיפורא ארעי Hai man de-nich-le de-tipura arei is one who wants his
field to be nice and clean.
What רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is saying is
that if I contract to plant one and not the other,
that's because the owner of the field knows I planted the other
the year before and not the one. So somebody, I can't go
and say okay I contracted to plant wheat but now I'm going
to plant barley because it's less bad, it might be bad because
last year you also planted barley. And so you should do it
the opposite. And so you can't go against your contract for that
reason.
Okay, that's the end of that section. Now we have תבואה לא
יזרענה קטנית Tivuah Lo Yizraena Kitni back from the משנה. Mishnah. It
isn't just between two different types of grains, it's also between cereals
and legumes. מתני ליה רב יהודה לרבין. Matni lei Rav Yehuda le-Rabin.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda taught רבין. Rabin. תבואה לא יזרענה קטנית. Tivuah
Lo Yizraena Kitni. Ah,
he says
the
opposite from the משנה. Mishnah. אמר ליה והא אנן תנן Amar lei
ve-ha-anan tenan תבואה לא יזרענה קטנית? Tivuah Lo Yizraena Kitni? But that
goes against the משנה, Mishnah, says the student. אמר ליה לא קשיא
הא לן והא להו.
Amar lei lo kashya.
Ha lan ve-ha le-hu. No,
it's not a problem. What I said is for us in בבל
Bavel and what the משנה Mishnah says is for them in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Happens all the time.
Now, why? So the נימוקי יוסף, Nimukei Yosef, so apparently there's a
difference according to the נימוקי יוסף, Nimukei Yosef, the difference is between
fields that are watered by rain and fields that are watered by
irrigation from rivers.
And בבל Bavel was obviously watered from irrigation from rivers because there's
major river systems in בבל. Bavel.
הרי יש חקלאות בעל מן הגשם.
Harei yesh
chaklaut baal min hageshem.
Yeah,
and so נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef raised the question, okay so we're
in Spain. Is Spain a rainy area or Spain done by irrigation?
He says okay, Spain is done by irrigation. No, but that's what
he said, wherever he, whatever נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef says, it's like
בבל, Bavel, that it's more like rivers, if I'm remembering that correctly,
I hope I'm right but I'm not going to check right now.
In any event, that
is the explanation of why they have the opposite opinion in בבל.
Bavel. אמר ליה רב יהודה לרבין בר רב נחמן. Amar lei Rav
Yehuda le-Rabin bar Rav Nachman. רבין אחי. Rabin achi. רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says to רבין בר רב נחמן, Rabin bar Rav Nachman, רבין
Rabin my brother, הני תחלי דבי כיתני hanei tachlei devei kitnei this
garden cress which is some sort of like vegetable that grows between
the פשתן, pishtan, grows among the flax, אין בהם משום גזל. ein
bahem mishum gezel.
There's no problem of stealing those. Why says רש"י? Rashi? Because it
actually damages the פשתן pishtan while it's growing. אם דקיימי אגבולין יש
בהם משום גזל. Im de-ad agvulei yesh mishum gezel
But if they're on the borders between fields, then it is problematic
to steal those because obviously a person wanted to grow garden cress
there because they planted it there. Garden cress apparently is like something
you can eat as an herb, it also was used in some
sort as a medicinal for medicinal purposes. אם דקיימי אגבולין Im de-ad
agvulim יש בהם משום גזל yesh bahem mishum gezel. ואם הוקשו לזרע
אפילו דבי כיתני נמי יש בהם משום גזל. ve-im hukshu le-zera afilu
devei kitnei nami yesh bahem mishum gezel. מאי טעמא מאי דאפסיד אפסיד.
Mai taama? Mai de-afsidei afsidei. Okay,
but if they've already hardened and they've grown their seeds,
then even when they're growing among the פשתן, pishtan, even when they're
growing among the flax, it's problematic to steal them. Why they say?
Because it's already done all the damage it's going to do. Once
it's hardened, it's fully grown, it's done the damage to the פשתן
pishtan and now okay, I have bad פשתן pishtan and good garden
cress. So don't steal my garden cress.
Great. אמר ליה רב יהודה לרבין בר רב נחמן. Amar lei Rav
Yehuda le-Rabin bar Rav Nachman. Another point. רבין אחי, Rabin achi, my
brother רבין, Rabin, הני דילי דילך ודילך דילי. hanei diley dilach u-dilach
diley. What's
mine is yours and what's yours is mine. And this isn't apparently
a nice thing to say. נהוג בני מצר. Nehog benei metzar. Ah,
it's because we're talking about a tree on the border between the
two between their two properties. אילן הנוטה לכאן לכאן והנוטה לכאן לכאן.
Ilan hanoteh le-kan le-kan ve-hanoteh le-kan le-kan. One that's leaning to one
side is for that side, one that's leaning to the other side
is to that side. דאתמר, De-itmar,
as we said, אילן העומד על המצר, ilan ha-omed al hametzar, a
tree that stands on the border between two fields. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, רב Rav says, הנוטה לכאן לכאן והנוטה לכאן לכאן. hanoteh le-kan
le-kan ve-hanoteh le-kan le-kan. רב Rav says like we just said that
if it's leaning to one side, that tree actually belongs to the
side to which it's leaning and if it's leaning to the other
side, it belongs to that side. ושמואל אמר
חולקין. U-Shmuel amar cholkin. שמואל Shmuel says no, it's not actually that,
it means that we split between them. מתיבי. Meitvei.
They responded to רב Rav which is really response to
also what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to some degree. אילן העומד
על המצר יחלוקו תיובתא דרב. Ilan ha-omed al hametzar yachloku. Tiuvta de-Rav.
Wait, we have a ברייתא Braita of some sort that says a
tree that stands on the border between two fields יחלוקו, yachloku,
you actually have to split just like שמואל Shmuel said. שמואל Shmuel
isn't just his opinion, שמואל Shmuel has a ברייתא Braita to back
him up.
Before we go on we have to figure out what a מצר
metzar is. A מצר metzar isn't just like a line,
or it might be a line, but what it really is is
some sort of mound that goes along the border between the two
fields. And
there's a מחלוקת machloket רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot about does that
mean that that mound constitutes some sort of intermediate space that belongs
to both בעלים ba'alim or
irrespective of whether there's a mound or not there's still an imaginary
line between them that designates the border and so we have to
deal with what belongs to whom.
This סוגיא sugya is no longer about,
right, we started out dealing with חטין לא יזרע שעורים chittin lo
yizra se'orim and קטנית לא יזרע תאנה. katanit lo yizra te'unah.
And those are still contractual issues between lessee and lessor.
Right. Now we've moved into a קובץ kovetz of אמר ליה רב
יהודה לרבין בר רב נחמן, Amar Lei Rav Yehuda Le'Rabin Bar Rav
Nachman, רבינא אחי, Ravina Achi, וכולי. ve'chulei.
So there are apparently a bunch of traditions of where רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda like said something to this other person
with this structure where it starts out רבינא אחי, Ravina Achi, my
friend, my brother, וכולי וכולי ve'chulei ve'chulei about some other issue. And
most of what we're going to talk about is going to be
about, we're going to talk about מצר metzar for a while and
then
the רבינא אחי Ravina Achi סוגיות sugyot so to speak.
Yes.
So we've moved on to that.
I'm sorry, could you just translate the words
הני תחלי דבי כתנא? hani tachlei de'vei kitna?
הני תחלי, hani tachlei, תחלי tachlei is garden cress. Garden cress, תחלא.
tachal. Garden cress?
I don't know what that is.
It's a plant.
It's a little green thing with white flowers.
Stems and flowers.
You put it in, yeah.
Lepidium sativum, I don't remember.
In Steinsaltz, that's what he said it was.
I assume that he got that out
of פשתן. pishtan. פשתן pishtan is flax. פשתן pishtan is
what we make linen out of.
So תחלא tachal that grows in פשתן pishtan is problematic. So
back to the issue about the מצר. metzar. We have a tree
that's growing on the מצר. metzar. רש"י שלנו, Rashi shelanu, the רש"י
Rashi on the page says we're dealing with something that's ממש על
המצר, mamash al hametzar, that's really on the border. And he's going
to say that the issue is where the שורשים shorashim are, where
the roots are, in part, and then the roots relative to where
the actual tree grows. And if the roots are on one side
and the tree is on another, that's what we're talking about. But
ממש, mamash, that the tree is planted over the border and there
could be roots on either side.
תוספות Tosafot seem to, when they disagree with רש"י, Rashi, seem to
have a version of רש"י Rashi which does not have על המצר
al hametzar in it, it has על צד המצר, al tzad hametzar,
next to the מצר, metzar, next to the borderline. And so it's
clear to, רש"י Rashi is impossible to understand for them because if
the tree is planted on one side and the שורשים shorashim are
on one side, it's very clear from other sources in בבא בתרא
Bava Batra especially in like, I think it's, we'll get there in
a few weeks,
in דף כ"ז daf kaf zayin in בבא בתרא Bava Batra that
שדי נופו בתר עיקרו. shadei nofor batar ikaro.
The top of the tree follows the bottom of the tree. Who
does the tree belong to? It belongs to where it was planted.
So what are you talking about רש"י, Rashi, that it's planted on
one side of the line?
רש"י שלנו, Rashi shelanu, the רש"י Rashi on the page talks about,
now I have to find it. אגני
דמצר נוטעי
דכאן ודכאן נוטים שורשים בצד זה,
aganei d'metzar not'ei de'kan
u'de'kan not'im shorashim be'tzad zeh,
no.
הנה, hineh, דילי דילך
ודילך דילי,
dilei dilakh
ve'dilakh dilei, which is
the original statement of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda to רבין בר נחמני,
Rabin bar Nachmani, בר רב נחמן. Bar Rav Nachman. יש באילנות שפירותיך
ובאילנותיך שפירותי ששדותינו זו לזו סמוכים. yesh be'ilnot she'peirotekha ve'be'ilnotekha she'peirotai she'sadotenu
zo le'zo semukhim. That our fields are so, they are,
so there are some of your trees that are actually mine and
some of my trees that are actually yours
because our fields are really right up once against one another and
the borderline with a little mound between, with the raised mound, has
a raised mound on it and the אילנות נטועים בהם. ilanot netu'im
bahem. And the אילנות ilanot are planted on the מצר. metzar. יש
מהם נטועים בשלי ששורשיהן כפפו ונטעו כולן לתוך שדך, yesh me'hem netu'im
be'sheli she'shorshekhen kaphaphuh ve'nat'u khulan le'tokh sadekha,
that really although it's on the מצר, metzar, there's a mound that
we've basically grown an orchard in between our fields, one line of
an orchard in between our fields, but the roots of one go
to one side and there are some where the roots go to
the other.
And so the tree might be popping up on one side of
the מצר metzar that it's like on the, over the imaginary borderline,
the tree's גזע geza is, the tree's trunk is over here, but
really the roots are over there.
So they take the water from
your, יונקים משלך yonkim mi'shelakha
is the issue.
So they take the water from the other. שנופין shenofin מתוך mitoch
שלי sheli ויונקין veyonkin מארצי, meartzi,
what does that mean?
I'll show you. Here. We're going to draw it so it works.
Okay. So here is our imaginary... this is our מיצר. meitzar. It's
some sort of
mound like the field over here and field over here. And then
over here we have a tree. Tree goes up.
And here's the imaginary מיצר meitzar line.
Goes around the tree. So really
according to Rashi it's on the מיצר, meitzar, which is the mound
between the two fields. But the roots, so it looks like the
tree is over here, the פירות peirot are all in my field.
But the roots are all growing to one side. So even though
the tree comes out on the other side, all of the nutrition
comes from this field. And there's another tree,
here the מיצר meitzar goes over here, we're going to say. There's
another tree
and all its fruit actually goes to this field, but all of
its roots go to that field. That's how Rashi explains the סוגיא.
suggya.
So you're saying that there's two trees. כאילו. Keilu. He says דילפתי
לי ודידי
דילך.
dilafte
li vedidi dilach.
There are some that are mine that are some that look like
mine that are actually yours, and there are some that look like
yours that are actually mine because of where the roots are according
to Rashi.
תוספות Tosafot say no, no, no, nonsense. Where the roots are determines
everything.
And a מיצר meitzar is shared space. And the roots...
firstly, there's no little imaginary line in the middle of the מיצר
meitzar according to תוספות. Tosafot.
So the roots don't determine everything?
The roots do determine everything, but the מיצר meitzar is a line
with no space. There's no area of the מיצר meitzar that's shared
space. תוספות Tosafot say, and this is sort of learned out from
תוספות, Tosafot, they don't say this quite explicitly, but it's assumed, the
roots are here
within the מיצר. meitzar. That the roots are shared, and that's why
in the rest of this סוגיא suggya that we haven't read yet,
it goes by where the fruit are.
Because the roots are in shared space. Or רב Rav has the
opinion that it goes by where the fruit are, even though we
reject that opinion and we say we actually split the fruits because
it's on shared land.
But so figuring out the facts of these various cases are all
attempts to concretize the principle הני דידי דילך ודילך דידי. hani dili
dilach dilach dili.
So that's not the principle. That is...
That sounds to me like a principle, no?
No, that is the... that would be the case... not the principle,
that's the conclusion. That's the practical conclusion in a case where according
to Rashi's interpretation,
the roots are on one side but the tree is on the
other. That it actually looks like yours but it's really mine, or
it looks like mine but it's really yours.
Now you want to say that
the real principle so to speak... yeah, the principle that we end
up coming to is
אילן הנטוע על המיצר, ilan hanatu al hameitzar, an אילן ilan planted
on the border mound
belongs to both owners on either side of the border between the
two fields, and the fruit is split.
That's שמואל. Shmuel. That's שמואל Shmuel and we פסקן pasken like שמואל.
Shmuel.
Wait, so sounds like this is the principle of what the הלכה
halacha in real estate of בר מצרא, barmatzra, you said.
בר מצרא's Barmatzra dealt with more on the next page.
Right, that's the issue. Your field is adjacent to mine, you have
to have first privileges to buy my field.
That's a different rule about
בר מצרא.
barmatzra. Same concept here of adjacent...
Right, we're dealing with the same reality,
yeah.
I just want you to go over one thing. You said תוספות
Tosafot said that it's actually on the border so where the fruits
lie, that's where they...
That's according to רב. Rav.
That's according to who? רב? Rav? I thought you said it was
תוספות. Tosafot.
תוספות Tosafot explaining how רב Rav can say. רב Rav said הנטוע
לכאן לכאן והנטוע לכאן לכאן. hanatu lachan lachan vehanatu lachan lachan.
And the
only way רב Rav could say that is in a case where
when we hold the מיצר meitzar is shared space, the trees are
planted ממש על המיצר, mamash al hameitzar,
but
the tree's fruit might go to one side or the other, the
branch.
שמואל Shmuel says
חולקין, chokin, and that becomes the הלכה halacha that we split the
fruits of an אילן ilan that is of a tree that's planted
on the border mound.
How would you ever know which side the roots went to?
That's a good question. By which I mean I have no idea.
Probably common sense.
Okay,
so okay. Now we need to go through the rest of the
סוגיא. suggya. Okay.
So we said מיתיבי, meitivei, a תיובתא דרב. tiyuvta de-Rav. We had
a ברייתא baraita that says חולקין. chokin. So how can רב Rav
say הנטוע לכאן לכאן והנטוע לכאן לכאן? hanatu lachan lachan vehanatu lachan
lachan? The ברייתא baraita says split. How can רב Rav disagree?
A good answer might be רב תנא ופליג. Rav tanna u-palig. רב
Rav is considered like sort of a half-תנא, tanna, and רב Rav
doesn't care about this ברייתא. baraita.
תרגמה שמואל אליבא דרב. Tirgaman Shmuel aliba de-Rav. Ah, we can explain
שמואל Shmuel as being according to רב. Rav. That there's some...
meaning שמואל Shmuel manages to explain this ברייתא baraita to fit רב?
Rav?
Yeah, it's or שמואל's Shmuel opinion can be explained according to רב
Rav that it's like there's some principle at play where
it's
הנטוע לכאן לכאן והנטוע לכאן לכאן. hanatu lachan lachan vehanatu lachan lachan.
In any event, here's how they try to do it: בממלא כל
המיצר כולו, b'memale kol hametzar kulo, where it's it's filling the entire
where it's and that's not something that I've managed to fully understand.
Let's read רש"י Rashi on what he says that is.
שנוטלים שרשים לכאן ולכאן, shenotim shoreshim l'kan u'l'kan, that there's שרשים shorshim
on both sides. That actually works for רש"י, Rashi, that it is
shared, which is how תוספות Tosafot explains the entire thing. And תוספות
Tosafot explains בממלא כל המיצר b'memale kol hametzar כמו שהשרשים הן כולן
על המיצר כך הן הענפים. kmo she'hashorshim hen kulan al hametzar kakh
hen ha'anafim. דתלי טעונה לחד, d'tali t'unei l'khad, that's the next thing.
That they say that they're ממש mamash בממלא כל המיצר, b'memale kol
hametzar, the roots are entirely within the מיצר, metzar, and that's the
case we have to be talking about. אי הכי מאי
למימרא, ei hachi mai l'meimra, but what why would you what does
that matter? says the גמרא. Gemara. It's like it's still the same
case, it's still יחלוקו. yakhloku. What does it teach us? מהו דתימא
דאמר ליה פלוג הכי, mahu d'teima d'amar leh p'log hachi, קא משמע
לן דאמר ליה מה חזית דפלגת הכי. ka mashma lan d'amar leh
mah khazit d'falagt hachi.
Sorry, that's the next thing. לא צריכא דתלי טעונה לחד גיסא. lo
tzricha d'tali t'unei l'khad gisa. What does it teach us? Oh, it
teaches us about the case where even though it goes off one
it goes up one place and the and the roots are entirely
in one part, according to רש"י, Rashi,
the sort of mass of fruit of the tree is דתלי טעונה
לחד גיסא. d'tali t'unei l'khad gisa. The טעונה t'una is the is
the load that the tree has, the load is on one side.
Wait, I thought that's what רש"י Rashi said to begin with. Yeah,
exactly.
Right.
And so he needs to teach us that case that it's on
the הנטלה
לכאן לכאן. hanotela l'kan l'kan.
That's what you believed it would be even with that case. I'm
sorry, so what what's the case?
Which case? The one שמואל Shmuel is now explaining?
שמואל Shmuel is now explaining why רב Rav would say הנטלה לכאן
לכאן. hanotela l'kan l'kan.
So when we say אילן
עומד על המיצר
יחלוקו, ilan omed al
hametzar yakhloku, I thought that that's
what
we were talking about.
Yeah, just a second.
So יחלוקו, yakhloku,
meaning the roots are on both sides but nevertheless the fruit is
on one side and that's what רב Rav would and that's what
the ברייתא braitah says יחלוקו. yakhloku.
Must be something like that.
They still, okay, so the גמרא Gemara still doesn't find this to
be a sufficient explanation. They say ואכתי מאי למימרא v'achti mai l'meimra
and
nevertheless what does this teach why would you ever say that? מהו
דתימא דאמר ליה פלוג הכי. mahu d'teima d'amar leh p'log hachi.
According to in
even though so now we're dealing with a case where it's the
שרשים shorshim are either on both sides of the line or it's
entirely within the border space.
Why would you tell me to go down the middle
when most of the fruit is on one side? שמואל Shmuel says,
ah, מה חזית דפלגת
הכי
פלוג הכי.
mah
khazit
d'falagt hachi
p'log hachi. You should teach you should go the other way. You
should go not down the middle of the border, you should go
across the border such that even though most of the fruit is
on one side, you cut through that mass opposite
wise, perpendicularly, and so really the fruit is properly split. So תרגם
לשמואל אליבא דרב turgam l'Shmuel aliba d'Rav is like a way
that שמואל Shmuel hints to רב. Rav. It's not
clear
and I haven't seen.
I mean, I don't get what
it means פלוג הכי p'log hachi and פלגת הכי. palagt hachi. מה
חזית, mah khazit, everyone agrees.
What are the two ways of cutting it? All the fruit is
on one side. You
have
a tree, next to the
tree
look
at all the fruit. Okay, really all the fruit
is
over here, and the שרשים shorshim
are
either הנטלה לכאן לכאן. hanotela l'kan l'kan. According to רש"י, Rashi, they're
on either side of the מיצר. metzar. According to תוספות, Tosafot, they're
entirely within the מיצר. metzar. Okay, all like really the mass of
fruit is in this side. So do we cut the tree when
we split, do we cut that way or do we cut that
way? Ah, לרוחב, l'rokhav, לרוחב. l'rokhav.
And so,
yeah, but what would be the סברא svara for doing it the
second way? All the fruit's on one side.
So why ah because because because the roots are equal. Ah, if
the roots are equal, the fruit the טעמא ta'ama would be that
the fruit should also be divided equally, so the way to do
that is to cut it this way,
horizontally, not vertically.
I'm still not understanding though. שמואל Shmuel is the one who says
יחלוקו.
yakhloku. רב Rav always says
הנטלה לכאן
לכאן.
hanotela l'kan
l'kan. What
is the thought process?
All the fruit is on the right hand side, right? And you
split it between right and left. But I thought...
wait, so why is רבא... Rava... so why is רבא... Rava... if
the roots are equal and even though the fruit is all on
one side, the roots are going to determine that you should divide
it horizontally
and that way each person gets half the amount of fruit. Does
that answer your question?
I do understand your question, the problem is I don't understand the
גמרא Gemara and the גמרא Gemara does not make sense.
After vast amounts of study, I determined that that was exactly
according to some of what you were drawing here. Yeah. This is
suggesting that the way to make the distribution equal is
to have it perpendicular, not horizontal.
Yeah, that's what...
so that's the perpendicular, not horizontal. That's horizontal. Perpendicular would be that
one. No,
this is along the path of the מיצר. meitzar. The מיצר meitzar
runs this way. And so if we cut it along the מיצר,
meitzar, we have unequal distribution. If we cut it perpendicularly where we
cut sort of through the side of the tree, so even though
the mass of it is over here, we have a whole mass
of things, if I cut it here,
then this side goes to me and this side goes to the
other side of the מיצר meitzar goes to you.
Yeah, but if all the tree's fruit's over there then that's not
distributing equally.
If we were...
let's try it 3D. Okay.
I don't want to...
sorry. Here's the מיצר. meitzar. Right. Here's all the fruit. If we
cut it... if we cut along the מיצר, meitzar, I would get
all the fruit. Exactly. So we say we cut it this way.
Exactly. Right. That's what this is trying to do.
This doesn't have the 3D aspect. Right. I'm still not sure what
תרגומא דשמואל אליבא דרבא, Targuma d'Shmuel aliba d'Rava, it seems like שמואל
Shmuel is still חולק cholek on
רבא Rava in a way that allows him to explain the... but
I'm really not...
what does חולק cholek mean?
חולק cholek means disagreeing.
Okay.
We're going to have to leave that aside and I'm sorry I
don't have a better way of explaining it.
It seems like
רש"י Rashi's explanation works better for this. Sorry, let's go back for
a moment. אילן העומד על המיצר אמר רב האי תלאי להאי גיסא
והאי תלאי להאי גיסא ושמואל אמר יחלוקו מיתיבי אילן העומד על המיצר
יחלוקו תיובתא דרב.
Ilan haomed al hameitzar amar Rav hai talai lehai gisa vehai talai
lehai gisa uShmuel amar yachaloku
meitivei ilan haomed al hameitzar yachaloku tiuvta deRav. How can רב Rav
say that we say it depends where the fruit is when we
say when the משנה Mishna says split? How can you say
split?
How do you split? You split according to...
where is it relevant? It's relevant when the entire...
all of the roots
are with... are on either side of the מיצר. meitzar. So it
looks like so that you can't really determine according to the roots,
you have to determine according to the fruit. Okay, so what does
שמואל Shmuel say? So what is it... why is the משנה Mishna
saying יחלוקו? yachaloku? When really it goes... really it's unfair that all
of the fruit... that a huge amount of the fruit is on
one side and so for equity we have to split the other
way.
That's what it has to be. אכתי פלוגתא היא. Achti pelugta hi.
Okay. אמר
ליה רב גידל לרב
נחמן רבין אחי לא תזבין ארעא דסמיכא למתא. Amar
lei Rav Gidal leRav
Nachman Ravin achi lo tazbin ara desmicha lemata.
He says again the same thing. Don't buy land that's near a
city. דאמר רב אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב אסור לו לאדם
שיעמוד על שדה חבירו בשעה שעומדת בקמותיה. Deamar Rav Abba amar Rav
Huna amar Rav asur lo leadam sheyamod al sdei chaveiro beshaa sheomedet
bekomateha. It is because רב אבא Rav Abba says in the name
of רב הונא Rav Huna and in the name of רב, Rav,
a person cannot... a person should not stand in the field of
his neighbor
when the fruit is in its standing point, when it's ready for
being cut. It's not good. איני? Ini? Is that really the case?
How... why can't... why do we really say? Why do we say
that it's... there's a problem to stand in your neighbor's field at
the at the point of harvest? ואשכחינהו רב אבא לתלמידי דרב. Veashkachinhu
Rav Abba letalmidi deRav.
We saw that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said to the student of
רב. Rav. אמר להו, Amar lehu, or
among them.
And he said to them, מאי אמר רב בהני קראי ברוך אתה
בעיר וברוך אתה בשדה ברוך אתה בבואך וברוך אתה בצאתך? Mai amar
Rav behanei krai baruch ata bair ubaruch ata basade baruch ata bevoacha
ubaruch ata betzeitecha? How did רב Rav interpret this sentence from דברים?
Devarim? Blessed are you in the city and blessed are you in
the field, blessed are you in your comings and in your goings.
ואמרו ליה הכי אמר רב ברוך אתה בעיר שיהא ביתך סמוך לבית
הכנסת.
Veamru lei hachi amar
Rav baruch ata bair sheyehe beitcha samuch leveit hakeneset. And they said
back to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, oh רב Rav said this.
Blessed are you in the city such that that your house is
near the synagogue. That's what
you'd... which means that you bought land near the city,
which is a problem for what רב Rav said otherwise, which is
you shouldn't buy land near the city. ברוך אתה בבואך, Baruch atah
bevo'echa, blessed are you in your comings, שלא תמצא אשתך ספק נדה
בשעת ביאתך מן
הדרך, shelo timtza ishtecha safek niddah b'sha'at bi'atcha min haderech,
that what does it mean to be blessed when you come home?
That you shouldn't find your wife in a doubtful state of נדה
niddah at the time when you come home. I've always wondered why
it seems like it's always ספק נדה safek niddah and it's...
ספק Safek is the word. Like in life, ספק safek is the
word.
But why not ממש נדה? mamash niddah?
Why isn't it...?
Because then you
know what to do.
ספק נדה Safek niddah you also know what to do.
לא חשוב. Lo chashuv.
Come to the ישיבה של
מטה.
yeshiva shel mata.
ספק, Safek, it always seems to me like ספק נדה safek niddah
you... it's like you know what to do and they're just not
saying נדה. niddah.
I don't understand,
meaning you figure out whether you're נדה niddah or not?
I think I assume that ספק נדה safek niddah is like
there's a clear way of deciding the case and not that there's
like ממש mamash I don't know what to do I need to
go ask a שאלה shaila and it's unclear and there are different
opinions. It doesn't mean...
it sounds like when I hear ספק, safek, I don't mean like
really no one knows what to do there are multiple opinions, it
means a ספק לחומרא. safek l'chumra.
And so we don't know and thus it's a חומרא chumra and
it's כאילו שהיא נדה. ke'ilu she'hee niddah. So then I don't know
why it's always saying ספק נדה. safek niddah.
Because then נדה niddah doesn't you, you know, it doesn't feel as
bad?
Like then, right? That there's like...
No, to me it feels the same. If it's ספק... safek...
No, also because if you're coming, maybe like you're coming from you're
expecting your wife not to be in נדה. niddah. Yeah. Just something
happened in the middle of the cycle and it's not supposed to
be נדה niddah and now she's ספק נדה safek niddah and you
have to like act like she's נדה niddah even though it's not
when she's supposed to be נדה, niddah, right? Like that would be
worse.
Yeah, I mean like that's what it means, but it just seems
strange to me to say that that should be the saying. Maybe
I just... I just don't have the experience of it. Okay. בשעת
ביאתך מן הדרך. B'sha'at bi'atcha min haderech. Next... I really don't want
to.
ברוך אתה בצאתך, Baruch atah betzeitecha, how is
it that your goings out are also blessed? שיצאו צאצאיך כמותך. Sheyetzei
tze'etza'echa k'motecha. That your children should be like you, your descendants should
be like you. ואמר לך, V'amar lach, or רבי יוחנן אמר הכי.
Rabbi Yochanan amar hachi. He said wait, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan didn't
say like that, אלא ברוך אתה בעיר. ella baruch atah ba'ir. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan disagreed with רב. Rav. Remember, this is still finding
the problem in רב's Rav statement, but it's part of another story
about different interpretations of this verse in דברים. Devarim. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan disagrees. ברוך אתה בעיר, Baruch atah ba'ir, what does it mean
to be blessed in the city? שיהא בית הכסא סמוך לשולחנך, Sheyehei
beit hakisse samuch l'shulchanacha, that your bathroom should be close to your
table. אבל בית הכנסת לא,
Aval beit haknesset
lo, but not the בית הכנסת. beit haknesset. רב Rav said that
you should be near your בית הכנסת, beit haknesset, you should be
near your שול. shul. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said no. Why
does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say לא? lo? רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, Rabbi
Yochanan l'taameih, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his opinion elsewhere,
שכר פסיעות יש. sachar pesiot yesh. You get essentially reward for the
amount you walk to the בית הכנסת. beit haknesset.
ברוך אתה בשדה, Baruch atah basadeh, what does it mean to be
blessed in the field according to
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? שיהיו נכסיך משולשין, Sheyehyu nechasyecha meshulashin, שליש בתבואה
שליש בזיתים ושליש בגפנים. shelish bitvu'ah shelish b'zeitim u'shelish b'gephanim. A third
of cereal, olives, and grapes. The Mediterranean triad, as we know, which
is דוקא davka wheat. ברוך אתה בבואך וברוך אתה בצאתך. Baruch atah
bevo'echa u'varuch atah betzeitecha. What does it mean in your goings out
and in your comings? שתהא יציאתך מן העולם כביאתך לעולם מה ביאתך
לעולם בלא חטא אף יציאתך מן העולם בלא חטא. Shetehei yetzi'atcha min
ha'olam k'vi'atcha la'olam ma bi'atcha la'olam belo cheit af yetzi'atcha min ha'olam
belo cheit. That leaving the world you should be without sin just
as you were without sin when you came into the world. So
this is part of this story of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba meeting
the students of רב Rav and רב Rav said his, רב's Rav
interpretation of the verse in דברים, Devarim, and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
said back their דרשה drasha of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan of the
verse in דברים. Devarim. לא קשיא. Lo kashya. Back to the issue
of רב Rav being... disagreeing with himself. הא דמהדר ליה שורא וריתקא
הא דלא מהדר ליה שורא וריתקא. Ha d'mehader lei shura v'ritka ha
d'lo mehader lei shura v'ritka. The one case where it's okay to
be in the field,
or it's okay to have your field right next to the city,
is when there's a wall. But you shouldn't have your field near
a city when there's no wall around the city. Okay.
והסיר ה׳ ממך כל חולי. Ve'hesir Hashem mimcha kol choli. Now we're
going back to just דרשות drashot of רב. Rav. What does it
mean God will remove from you all illness? אמר רב זו עין.
Amar Rav zo ayin. This is the evil eye. רב לטעמיה. Rav
l'taameih. This is רב Rav according to his general approach. דרב סליק
לבי קברי עבד מאי דעבד. De'Rav salik l'vei kavrei avid mai d'avid.
רב Rav would go into the cemetery and he would do a
thing, רש״י Rashi claims doing a thing is some sort of magic
to learn about or talk to the dead people.
אמר Amar 99 of them died of the evil eye and one
normally.
שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar, what does it mean והסיר ה' ממך כל
חולי? V'heisir Hashem mimcha kol choli? What is this חולי? choli? What
is this illness that God will remove from you? וזה הרוח, V'zeh
haruach, it's the wind. שמואל לטעמיה, Shmuel l'taameih, this is Shmuel according
to his approach, דאמר שמואל הכל ברוח. d'amar Shmuel hakol beruach.
Everything is a problem because of the wind. ולשמואל האיכא הרוגי מלכות?
U'l'Shmuel ha-ika harugei malchut? What does it mean the wind causes problems?
There are people who are killed by the government, there are people
who are killed by the Romans. התם נמי אלמלא זיקא עבדי להו
סמא וחיי. Hatam nami ilmalei zika avdei lehu sama v'chayei. Ah, so
if it hadn't been for the wind which would have made everything
worse, we would have had some sort of special ointment that would
have put their body back together and they would have survived, which
is how רש"י Rashi explains
עבדי להו סמא וחיי. avdei lehu sama v'chayei. סמא Sama is a
drug. Here it's explained as some sort of ointment that allows the
body to heal better.
It seems to me a great deal more than was plausible. In
any event, that's how we explain שמואל's Shmuel opinion. רבי חנינא אמר
זו צינה. Rabbi Chanina amar zo tzina. What is the חולי? choli?
What is the illness of the verse in דברים? Devarim? This is
cold. דאמר רבי חנינא הכל בידי שמים חוץ מצנים פחים. D'amar Rabbi
Chanina hakol b'yedei Shamayim chutz mitzinim pachim. Everything is in the hands
of Heaven except for, here it probably means cold drafts, but in
the verse he's about to cite, it means thorns and snares. שנאמר
צנים פחים בדרך עקש שומר נפשו ירחק
מהם.
She'ne'emar tzinim pachim b'derech ikeish
shomer nafsho yirchak meihem. There are thorns and snares in the way
of the crooked one, one who guards himself will distance himself from
them. Good. רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר. Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina amar.
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, there's a fourth opinion about what the חולי
choli from the verse in דברים Devarim is. זו צואה. Zo tzoah.
This is excretion from the body. דאמר מר צואת החוטם וצואת האוזן
רובן קשה ומיעוטן יפה. D'amar mar tzoat hachotem u'tzoat ha-ozen ruban kasheh
u'miutan yafeh. Because we have another opinion of
the master, רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina,
that the excretions of the nose and the excretions of the ear,
most of them are bad and some of them are okay.
רבי אלעזר אמר זו מרה. Rabbi Elazar amar zo marah. What is
the חולי choli again, finally, that the verse in דברים Devarim is
talking about that Hashem will remove from us? This is the gall,
this is bile. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami hachi. Oh, we have
a ברייתא Beraita that agrees with רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. מחלה זו
מרה. Machalah zo marah. When we talk about מחלה, machalah, which is
the same word that's used in the verse to talk about חולי,
choli, זו מרה zo marah refers to the problems of the gall,
refers to bile. ולמה נקרא שמה מחלה? U'lamah nikra shemah machalah? Okay,
why are we calling מרה, marah, which is only part of the
body, one of only the four humors,
why is it called מחלה, machalah, why is it called illness in
general? שהיא מחלה כל גופו של אדם. She'hi machalah kol gufo shel
adam. Because it really hurts the entire body of a person. דבר
אחר מחלה ששמונים ושלושה חלאים תלויין במרה.
Davar acher machalah
she'shmonim u'shlosha cholayim tluyin b'marah. It's called מחלה machalah because there are
שמונים ושלושה shmonim u'shlosha 83 illnesses that come from the bile or
come from the gallbladder. וכולן פת שחרית במלח וקיתון של מים מבטלתן.
V'kulan pat shacharit b'melach v'kiton shel mayim mevatlatan. מרה Marah is
bile. Bile. Like the gallbladder. The gallbladder is part of מרה. marah.
No, no. Yeah, so מרה, marah, so the gall is what produces
bile. And bile is one of the four humors, and remember part
of their science is that you have four humors and when they're
out of balance that's what causes illness. And there are four presumably
caused by an excess of bile or there's a problem with the
bile, there's a problem with the gallbladder, and thus these cause problems,
it's called מחלה machalah in general, just in illness is caused by
the bile,
is caused by the gallbladder. And then they also have a source
that says furthermore there are 83 illnesses that come from the gallbladder,
they come from bile, and every one of them פת שחרית במלח
וקיתון של מים מבטלתן, pat shacharit b'melach v'kiton shel mayim mevatlatan, a
bit of bread in the morning and a jug of water makes
it better.
And now we're going to talk a lot about פת שחרית. pat
shacharit. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
This is a very interesting
הלכה, halacha, פת שחרית.
pat shacharit. פת שחרית.
Pat shacharit. Have to be careful.
It's not פוט שחרית, pot shacharit, I think. Bread.
Cereal. Yeah, cereal, it's breakfast. Bread.
As I said,
breadfast.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
שלושה עשר דברים נאמרו בפת שחרית. Shlosha asar devarim neemru b'fat shacharit.
There were 13 wonderful things said about the bread, about your morning
toast. מצלת מן החמה, Matzelet min hachamah, it saves you from the
sun, ומן הצינה, u'min hatzina, and from the warmth and from the
cold, ומן הזיקין, u'min hazikin, and from bad winds, ומן המזיקין, u'min
hamazikin, and from demons, ומחכימת
פתי, u'machkimat peti, and it widens the mouth, וזוכה בדין, v'zocha badin,
and it allows you to succeed in court cases, וללמוד תורה, u'lilmod
Torah, to learn Torah, וללמד, u'lelamed, and to teach Torah, ודבריו נשמעין,
u'devarav nishma'in,
and his תפילות tefillot are heard by God, ותלמודו מתקיים בידו, v'talmudo
mitkayem b'yado, and he remembers what he learned, which is really hard,
ואין בשרו מעלה הבל, v'ein besaro ma'aleh hevel, and his body doesn't
have a fever, or it doesn't raise heat, ונזקק לאשתו ואינו מתאווה
לאשה אחרת, v'nizkak l'ishto v'eino mitaveh l'ishah acheret, and he's only attracted
to his wife and not to anybody else, any other woman, והורגת
כינה שבבני מעיים, v'horeget kinah she'be'vnei mei'ayim, and it also kills worms
that you have in your belly.
ויש אומרים. V'yesh omrim.
יש אומרים
אף מוציאה את הקנאה ומכניסה את האהבה
yesh omrim af motziah
et hakinah umachnisah et ha'ahavah even takes out jealousy and brings in
love. How wonderful. אמר ליה רבה לרבא בר מרי amar lei Rabbah
l'Rava bar Mari המילתא דאמרי אינשי ha milta d'amri inshi שיתין רהיטי
רהיט ולא מטו לגברא דמצפרא כרך shittin rehitai rehit v'lo matu l'gavra
d'mitzpara kerach ואמרו רבנן v'amru rabanan השכם ואכול בקיץ מפני החמה ובחורף
מפני הצינה. hashkem ve'echol bakayitz mipnei hachamah uvachoref mipnei hatzinah. So Rabbah
says to Rava bar Mari, what is it, where do we get
this idea that people say? Firstly, there's apparently a common saying: Sixty
runners can't catch up to a guy who ate his morning bread.
And furthermore, the rabbis say, השכם ואכול בקיץ מפני החמה ובחורף מפני
הצינה, hashkem ve'echol bakayitz mipnei hachamah uvachoref mipnei hatzinah, get up and
eat in the summer because of the heat and in the winter
because of the cold. Where is the source? אמר ליה דכתיב amar
lei dechtiv לא ירעבו ולא יצמאו ולא יכם שרב ושמש. lo yire'avu
v'lo yitzmau v'lo yakeim sharav vashamesh. It says in Isaiah, they will
not be hungry and they will not be thirsty and they wouldn't
be hurt by cold and by the sun. לא יכם שרב ושמש,
lo yakeim sharav vashamesh, כיון דלא ירעבו ולא יצמאו. keivan d'lo yire'avu
v'lo yitzmau. Ah, it's like they're תלויה זה בזה. teluyim zeh bazeh.
You're not going to be hurt by the wind and by the
cold and the heat because they're not going to be hungry and
thirsty because they got up in the morning and they ate bread-fast
as we're calling it, they got up in the morning and they
had their their bread and their and their water.
That's going to save them from cold and heat. אמר ליה אנת
אמרת לי מהתם. amar lei ant amart li mehatam. Okay, you have
that source, I have a better source.
ואנא אמינא לך מהכא. v'ana amina lach mehacha.
I have a better source. ועבדתם את ה' אלהיכם וברך את לחמך
ואת מימיך. va'avadtem et Hashem Elokeichem uverach et lachmecha v'et meimecha. ועבדתם
את ה' אלהיכם. va'avadtem et Hashem Elokeichem.
Two verses say, and you shall serve the Lord your God and
bless your bread and your water. ועבדתם את ה' אלהיכם va'avadtem et
Hashem Elokeichem and then, sorry, that's the next פסקה, piska, you shall
serve the Lord your God and bless your water and your bread.
What does it mean you shall serve the Lord your God? זו
קריאת שמע ותפילה. zo kriyat shema utefilah. This is reading the Shema
and saying the Amidah. וברך את לחמך ואת מימיך. uverach et lachmecha
v'et meimecha. זו פת במלח וקיתון של מים. zo pat bemelach vekiton
shel mayim.
This is bread dipped in salt and a jug of water. מכאן
ואילך, mikan va'eilach, in the rest of the verse it says, והסירותי
מחלה מקרבך, vahasiroti machalah mikirbecha, I will remove machlah from among you,
I will remove illness from among you. How very lovely.
Doing things, doing this, I want to I too would like to
share with the group okay from my Tunisian North African Siddur after
Shacharit there's a page that says פת שחרית. pat shacharit. טוב שירגיל
האדם את עצמו באכילת פת שחרית tov sheyargil ha'adam et atzmo be'achilat
pat shacharit כדאמרינן בגמרא kedamrinan begemara and this סוגיא sugya and it
shows
it's according to this in the siddur.
I thought I should bring wheat bread so to speak. I thought
I'd share that with the group.
That's good. Okay.
More connected to everybody.
This this little teaching reminds me also of
there's this סוגיא sugya in ברכות Berachot about that you're not supposed
to eat before you daven which is very hard to do but
this is the same סברא sevara that it comes in
order that they're תלויה זה בזה, teluyim zeh bazeh, you have to
do them both but you have to daven before you eat.
Two sources of nourishment.
Yeah. Okay. אמר ליה רב יהודה לרב אדא משוחאה. amar lei Rav
Yehudah l'Rav Adda meshucha'ah. Rav Yehudah said to Rav Adda the surveyor,
לא תזלזל במשיחתא. lo tizalzel bemishchata. Don't be not careful, so be
careful when you survey and you take measurements. כל פורתא ופורתא חזי
לכורכמא דרישקא. kol purta upurta chazi l'churkama derishka. Every little piece of
land could be used to plant saffron, which as we know then
as now was really really expensive and really really important in food.
More expensive in India so they say.
Well it's still expensive here. אמר ליה רב יהודה לרב אדא משוחאה,
amar lei Rav Yehudah l'Rav Adda meshucha'ah, furthermore, ארבע אמות דאניגרא זילזל
בהו. arba amot d'anigra zilzel behu. Okay, the four amot around a
bit of water that's brought in by irrigation from the river. That
you can be not careful about. Rashi explains because that area in
the field actually belongs to the owners of the field and to
the various owners of this tract of land that they've built the
irrigation system for and they'll be okay if you sort of miss
out here or there and they because it's privately owned by a
group of people they can be מוחל, mocheil, they can say that's
okay. However, דנהרא
לא תמשח כלל.
denahara lo timshach
klal. You shouldn't don't measure at all. רב יהודה לטעמיה דאמר רב
יהודה. Rav Yehudah l'taameih d'amar Rav Yehudah.
This is Rav Yehudah's opinion according to his general approach for Rav
Yehudah said ארבע אמות דאניגרא לבני אניגרא arba amot d'anigra livnei anigra
as we said, the four amot around the water source within the
field actually belong to the people in the field. ודנהרא דכולי עלמא.
udenahara dechulei alma. But on the but on the river belong to
everybody and so you have to be careful about it. מכריז רבי
אמי. machriz Rabbi Ami. Rabbi Ami announced,
disagreeing,
not disagreeing, a different point, מלא כתפי נגדי בתרי עברי נהרא קוצו.
mlo kitfei nagdei bitrei evrei nahara kutzu. You should cut down any
vegetation and trees the amount that it takes for people pulling barges
along the river to stand on the river stand on the riverbanks
on both sides. Ah,
רב
נתן
בר שריא Rav Natan bar Sharya קץ שיתסר אמתא. katz shitsar amta.
He didn't do that much, that's only a few אמות. amot. He
did a whole 16 אמות amot on either side. אתו עלי בני
משרוניא דפנוהו. atu alei bnei Mashrunya dafnu-hu. But the people of a
certain of the town of Mashrunya came and knocked him out. They
said they didn't like that. הוא סבר רשות הרבים hu savar reshut
harabim that the side he thought that the sides of a river
are actually public are actually the public domain.
And a public domain we know from elsewhere as Rashi explains has
to be 16 אמות amot wide and so he says, okay, the
sides of the river belong to everybody even if your field is
there, so it's not really your field, the sides of the river
space for everybody to work and that needs to be 16 אמות
amot wide on either side.
Ah, what's the problem with that? הוא סבר רשות הרבים ולא היא
התם בעינא כולי האי הכא משום אמתוחי אשליהן הוא כמלא כתפי נגדי
סגי.
hu savar reshut harabim velo hi hatam be'ina
kulei hai hacha mishum amtuchei ashleihen hu kemalei kitfei nagdei sagi. Ah,
over there in the actual רשות הרבים reshut harabim in the actual
street you need 16 אמות amot to move through. Here we don't
need even though it's public space you don't need 16 אמות. amot.
You only need enough for the people who are working there to
pull the barges along to get their long their long ropes stretched
out on that space so they can walk along. So there's different
so even though it is רשות הרבים reshut harabim there are different
things that function as public space for different purposes and there are
different amounts of physical space required for each one. רבה בר רב
הונא הוה ליה ההוא אבא אגודא דנהרא.
Rabba bar Rav Huna hava
leh hahu aba aguda denahara. Rabba bar Rav Huna actually himself had
a forest that he owned which was on the side of a
river. אמרו ליה ניקוץ מר. amru leh nikutzu mar. And they said
to
him you should, you know, cut down near the river because that's
the rule, you need to leave space for people to pull their
barges.
קוצו עילאי ותתאי והדר ניקוץ אנא. kutzu ilai vetatai vehadar nikutzu ana.
You know, he says, if the people above me and below me
on the river will do it, then I'll do it. But otherwise,
I'm not going to do this.
היכי עביד הכי? heichi avid hachi? What are you talking about? You
don't you have a חיוב chiyuv to do that? What are you
talking about that it depends on other people to do it first?
You should do it now. הא כתיב התקוששו וקושו. ha ketiv hitkosheshu
vakoshu. It
we have a פסוק pasuk that says gather and gather, gather yourselves
together and gather. אמר ריש לקיש קשוט עצמך ואחר כך קשוט אחרים.
amar Resh Lakish kshot atzmecha ve'achar kach kshot acherim. You should adorn
yourselves and then do it for other people. You should do what
everybody has to do this. Why are you waiting for other people?
Put you should take you should put the oxygen mask on yourself
before you put it on a baby, like the airplane ads always
say,
because if you don't do it yourself you'll pass out on the
plane. But in here we're saying there's just a חיוב chiyuv to
do yours first. You can't wait for other people to do something
that's required of everybody.
But it just expanded to other situations like the airplane. It's just
a a thing.
Yeah. התם אבא דבי פרזק רופילא הוה דאמר אי קייצי
קאיצנא ואי לא
קייצי לא קאיצנא.
hatam aba devei Parzak Rofila hava de'amar ei kaitzi
kaitzna ve'ei lo kaitzi lo kaitzna. Oh, why was he there why
did he say differently in his case? Why was Rabba bar Rav
Huna lenient on himself so to speak?
The other that land near him of the other people that he
was waiting for them to do it actually belonged to a guy
named פרזק Parzak who was a who was a some sort of
a general. And he didn't want to do that. He wasn't going
to do that.
And if he were if that other person, this big general, was
going to cut down his field, I'll cut down my field too.
But he's not going to and it's really not worthwhile for me
to do it, it's just a waste of my time
in
that special case.
דאי ממטו להו אשליהו מסגי להו. de'ei mamtu lehu ashlei-hu masgei lehu.
If they have enough space to spread out their ropes,
then that's enough for me. ואי לא לא מסגי להו. ve'ei lo
lo masgei lehu.
If they have enough space on this side, that's okay. But if
they don't have enough space in the other person's field, if they
don't have enough space
in the other person further up the river, further down the river,
just the fact that they have enough space in my area they're
not going to continue walking they're not going to come they're not
going to see 'oh, here's a little bit of patch on the
other side of the river that I can walk on, let's skip
to the other side of the river and pull from that side.'
No, they're going to continue walking along the along the other side
of the river where there is enough space for them to pull
their barges. And they're not going to come to my side. So
if because the other space the other parts on my side of
the river are never going to have room near me for people
to walk and pull their barges,
then it's irrelevant whether I do this whether I do this because
nobody else is going to. They're just going to stay on the
other side even if I did it. It's not going to accomplish
its purpose. That gets us to the top of כח עמוד א.
kaf chet amud aleph. Can I see your גמרא Gemara for a
second?
Ah,
okay.
All right, so apparently what we missed going back to the thing
on כ"ז עמוד א' Kaf-Zayin Amud-Aleph of תרי גווני משתעבדי לרב trei
gavnei mishta'abdei le-Rav is that there are times when Rav agrees that
you split the- that you split the produce. That when it's ממלא
כל המיצר, memalei kol hameitzer, going back remember we had this thing
about a tree that's planted on the boundary mound, according to רש"י
Rashi it was the- the roots go to both sides, and according
to תוספות Tosafot the roots are entirely within the boundary line, and
you would split there because it's ממלא כל המיצר. memalei kol hameitzer.
And thus so like why does it ממלא כל המיצר, memalei kol
hameitzer, why does he need to- why does he agree there? Ah,
sometimes there are going to be cases where even though it's- even
though the roots are equally split, the fruit is not equally split
and so I need to split it differently in order to have
an even distribution of fruit of the shared tree.
Just to go back and make sure that we got that in
because apparently I forgot what it was,
and that takes us to the end for today.